Start today with דף ט"ז Daf Tes Zayin 16. We pick up
from the very bottom of ט"ו עמוד ב'. Tes Vav Amud Bet.
Okay. כלל של דבר דרישא, Klal Shel Davar De-Reisha, literally the last
line. We basically have a ברייתא Baraisa that completely reviewed the משנה
Mishnah with a little elaboration about the difference between a קרבן Korban
that was first sanctified of, or was first had a מום Mum
and then sanctified so the קדושה Kedushah was never קדושת מזבח Kedushas
Mizbe'ach as opposed to one that was first sanctified and then had
a מום Mum and had a nice wrap-up sentence which said כלל
של דבר, Klal Shel Davar, the sort of, the general principle is
that in the first case what had a מום Mum and then
was redeemed, it's חולין לכל דבריהם, Hulin Le-Chol Divreihem, it totally has
no residual קדושה, Kedushah, it's complete חולין, Hulin, and in the second
case, even after it's redeemed, it still has קדושה. Kedushah. So now
the גמרא Gemara is just going to comment on the end, on
those summary lines of the ברייתא. Baraisa. כלל של דבר דרישא לאתויי,
Klal Shel Davar De-Reisha L'atuyei, what's the general rule is of the
first case where it's once it's redeemed it has no קדושה? Kedushah?
What's that including? לאתויי לחולין ששחטן בחוץ דפטור L'atuyei Le-Chullin She-Shachtam Ba-Chutz
De-Patur that when you slaughtered it outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
you're exempt. Of course the funny thing there is that it's exempt
even before it's redeemed because it never had קדושת קרבן. Kedushas Korban.
Okay, so that's anyway a case that was, that is the הלכה
Halacha of the first half, but it was not mentioned explicitly, so
that's what the כלל Klal is coming to include. The גמרא Gemara
is working with the assumption that anytime a משנה Mishnah ברייתא Baraisa
says a כלל, Klal, this is the rule, then it's coming to
teach you another הלכה Halacha that was not explicit, rather than just
to teach you sort of the principle of the matter.
So anyway,
so that's that, דפטור. De-Patur.
כלל של דבר דסיפא לאתויי, Klal Shel Davar De-Seifa L'atuyei, how about
top of ט"ז עמוד א'? Tes Zayin Amud Aleph? How about the
principle, this is the principle of the end of it that says
that an animal that started with קדושה Kedushah then got a מום
Mum is like קדשים לכל דבריהם? Kodshim Le-Chol Divreihem? חלבו, Halavo, not
חלבו Chelvo which is the fat, חלבו Halavo is milk, that the
same way the children are forbidden even after they were, if they
were born after it was redeemed, it was pregnant before it was
redeemed and they were born after, we spent the whole day yesterday
talking about that, the children are also, so here too the same
would be true by the milk. Okay. Now אמר מר, Amar Mar,
we're going to go back and look at that ברייתא. Baraisa. אין
פודין תמימים, Ein Pofdin Temimim, these animals that were first had קדושת
מזבח Kedushas Mizbe'ach and then got a מום Mum and then they
had, and then they gave birth to kids, they were redeemed and
gave birth. So it says they cannot be redeemed unblemished because you
don't redeem a קרבן Korban without a blemish. The kids, meaning the
mother's, and Michael made this point at the end of yesterday, the
mothers obviously had a blemish, that's the whole scenario, but then after
they were redeemed they gave birth and the kids don't have a
blemish. So the קדושה Kedushah on the one hand you can't redeem
them without a blemish, since when do you, can you redeem an
animal that's unblemished? On the other hand, as the גמרא Gemara went
to length to point out yesterday, you can't do anything with them
the way they are because they come from a קדושה Kedushah of
their mother which would not let it be brought as a קרבן.
Korban. You can't add a, you can't make something that's been pushed
away from a קרבן Korban as a קרבן. Korban. This has a
קדושה Kedushah of the mother which was sort of pushed away from
a קרבן. Korban. So you're basically stuck and you can't do anything
with it. But so, but so that's what the first line, you
can't redeem it without a blemish and you can't do anything with
it without it being redeemed, so you're totally stuck. ואין מתפיסין לכל
זבח שירצה V'ein Matpisin Le-Chol Zevach She-Yirtzeh and then the ברייתא Baraisa
we read yesterday also said you cannot sanctify them for a different
קרבן, Korban, which obviously suggests that you can give them the sanctity
for the קרבן Korban of the mother. And if you remember what
we said yesterday, that was the basic solution. If this fetus is
born after you redeem the mother, it's going to be sort of
caught between categories and you're going to be stuck. So what do
you do? Before you redeem the mother, you sanctify it as the
same קרבן Korban of the mother and therefore once it's born it
has independent קרבן Korban sanctity, independent because you sanctified it and it
can be brought as the קרבן. Korban. So that seems to be
suggested here by the ברייתא Baraisa because the ברייתא Baraisa says don't
give them a different sanctity, suggesting you can give them the same
sanctity of the mother. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is now
going to say. תמימים הוא דלא מיפרקי, Temimim Hu De-Lo Mifreki,
so the ברייתא Baraisa says you don't redeem them unblemished, הא בעלי
מומים מיפרקי Ha Ba'alei Mumim Mifreki suggests that once they develop a
blemish you can redeem them. So let's file that away, but that's
curious because we've been assuming that these animals that were born after
the mother's redeemed can never be, can never be salvaged even with
a blemish, but the implication of the ברייתא Baraisa is that with
a blemish it can. So we'll get back to that. Now let's
look at the next statement.
לכל זבח שירצה הוא דלא מתפיסין, Le-Chol Zevach She-Yirtzeh Hu De-Lo Matpisin,
you can't sanctify them for any, for any זבח Zevach you want,
הא לאותו זבח מתפיסין, Ha Le-Oso Zevach Matpisin, but for the same
זבח Zevach as the mother you can sanctify. So the implication of
this ברייתא Baraisa of these fetuses that then get born to these
when the mother had קדושה Kedushah and was redeemed, it says you
can't redeem them unblemished which means at blemish you can, you can't
sanctify them for a different sacrifice which means you can sanctify them
for the same sacrifice. You put them together and now we understand
the scenario, what's the scenario? Let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says... So the גמרא Gemara says היכי משכחת לה, heichi mashkachat
lah, so how does this work out? דמטפיסן לאותו זבח, dematpisan le'oto
zevach, you sanctify the fetus in its mother's womb for the same
קרבן korban as the mother, if the mother was going to be
a שלמים, shelamim, the fetus is a שלמים. shelamim. And then it's
born, then it has its own קדושה, kedushah, then you can bring
it as a שלמים, shelamim, and if then it develops a blemish,
וניפדין במומן, venifdin bemuman, you can redeem them with their blemish. So
basically, the implication of the ברייתא braita is that what do you
do in this difficult complex case? It says you can't give them
another sanctity, the implication is you can give them the same sanctity,
which is exactly the solution that the גמרא Gemara said yesterday. You
give them their own sanctity while they're still in their mother's womb,
as long as it's the same type of קרבן. korban. And then
it also says there's no solution to redeem it, but we said
yesterday there's no way to redeem it, but this implies you can
redeem it once it gets a blemish. What's the scenario? When you
gave them their own sanctity. Instead of what? Any other קרבן? korban?
Exactly. Just to say that ultimately when you give them their own
sanctity you'll solve the problem. Either you'll bring it as its own
קרבן korban or you'll be able to redeem it if it develops
a blemish. Okay, so the implication of that ברייתא braita was exactly
like רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, who was it said that yesterday? Like
רב חנינא Rav Chanina said it, that that's, that you sanctify them
right before they're born. Now the גמרא Gemara says, but that's a
challenge on רב הונא. Rav Huna. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב הונא, leima
tehevei tiyuvta deRav Huna,
maybe this is a contradiction to רב הונא Rav Huna because רב
הונא Rav Huna did not adopt רב חנינא's Rav Chanina's approach. רב
הונא Rav Huna said you can, never said you could sanctify them
before they're born. Remember what רב הונא Rav Huna said? רב הונא
Rav Huna said, Steve, so we were missing you yesterday, I'm glad
you're here. You were the voice, the voice of conscience, because רב
הונא Rav Huna said you lock them in a room and you
let them die. Okay, so, so he, but the ברייתא braita suggests
you can give them their own sanctity, and then if they develop
a blemish afterwards you can even redeem them. So this ברייתא braita
supports רב חנינא, Rav Chanina, it's a contradiction to רב הונא. Rav
Huna. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רב הונא, amar lach
Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna would say to you: הוא הדין
דאפילו בעלי מומין אין נפדין. hu hadin de'afilu ba'alei mumin ein nifdin.
You know what, you misread that ברייתא. braita. Even there's never a
scenario that they could be redeemed with a blemish. So why did
it say don't redeem them unblemished?
איידי דתני רישא נפדין תמימים, aidi detani reisha nifdin temimim, since in
the first scenario when the mother never had קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban,
when it started with a מום mum and then got sanctified and
then it had birth, and in that category if the kids even
if the kids are unblemished you can redeem them because the kids
never had קדושת מזבח. kedushas mizbeiach. So since in the first case
it talks about redeeming the kids unblemished, תני נמי סיפא אין נפדין
תמימים, tani nami seifa ein nifdin temimim, the second case you can't
redeem the kids unblemished, but the reality is you can't even redeem
them with a blemish. It's just that you can't do them unblemished
because in the first case it said you could even do it
unblemished.
I'm sorry, wait, what about giving them a
קדושה?
kedushah? Without just talk about that. ואיידי דתני רישא לכל זבח שירצה,
ve'aidi detani reisha lechol zevach sheyirtzeh,
since the רישא reisha said that when it came to, again, the
kids that were born to a mother that never had real קדושת
מזבח kedushas mizbeiach and that was redeemed and then became totally desacralized
and there it said that when it has the kids you can
make them any קרבן korban you want, you're not limited by the
קרבן korban of the mother, תני נמי סיפא לכל זבח שירצה, tani
nami seifa lechol zevach sheyirtzeh, so again it said
here you can't do for any קרבן korban you want. But what
it really means is you can't do it at all. So why
does the end say you can't do for any קרבן korban you
want? Not to suggest you can do it for the same קרבן
korban as the mother, but because in the beginning we said any
one you want, here we said it can't be anyone you want.
But it really can't be anything. And because the רישא reisha said
you can redeem things unblemished, the kids, here it says you can't
redeem them unblemished. But in reality you can't redeem them at all.
So basically it's a little imprecise but it really, there's no solution.
And because there's no solution, רב הונא Rav Huna said you'll have
to lock them up in the room. But again, the better solution
of רב חנינא, Rav Chanina, and it's not clear why he doesn't
even like רב חנינא, Rav Chanina, but the better solution of רב
חנינא Rav Chanina seems to be, and seems to be more suggested
in this ברייתא, braita, is you give them their own sanctity in
the mother's womb, so then when they're born they're their own קרבן,
korban, it's not defined by the mother, and then you either bring
it as a קרבן korban or if it develops a blemish you
can redeem it. Why does רב הונא Rav Huna can't do any
of that? Again, it's not totally clear why. רש"י Rashi says maybe
that's the גמרא's Gemara's answer we're afraid you'll raise flocks of them,
is explaining רב הונא Rav Huna why he doesn't like רב חנינא's
Rav Chanina's solution because that would take, somehow that'll take too long,
and by the time you're, and by the time you get around
to it, you're going to have children and children of children and
so on and that'll lead to you accidentally sinning. But anyway, that
is the end of that discussion. Now we move on, move on
in the ברייתא braita or in the משנה Mishnah to things which
are, I think, a little bit more accessible, a little not as
complex. So it says, והשוחטן בחוץ פטור. vehashochtan bachutz patur. Now, if
you shecht them outside בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, these animals that were
sanctified, then got a blemish, and then maybe yes or not redeemed,
okay, so it says פטור. patur. Now, the question is what line
is this going on? Our משנה Mishnah says השוחטן בחוץ חייב. hashochtan
bachutz chayav. Okay,
and that's talking about an animal that was sanctified, got a blemish,
not redeemed, sanctified, got a blemish, and then you shechted it outside
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And our משנה mishna said חייב. chayav.
Here we're saying פטור. patur. What is this, where's this line coming
from? It could be a different text of the משנה. mishna. And
we'll see there's actually a discussion in the גמרא Gemara what the
text was, חייב chayav or פטור. patur. But רש"י Rashi says that
after these few lines, the גמרא Gemara is going to double back
to talk about the ברייתא braita we've been discussing. So רש"י Rashi
actually claims that this was a version of the ברייתא braita we
just quoted. Remember, we just yesterday ended with a big ברייתא braita
that basically reviewed all of the laws of the משנה. mishna. That
ברייתא braita did not explicitly discuss שוחטי חוץ, shochtei chutz, but רש"י
Rashi says we're talking in the context of the ברייתא. braita. So
either way, either it's a different version of the משנה mishna or
within the context of the ברייתא, braita, we have a statement that
this animal that was sanctified and then developed a blemish and you
שחט shecht outside, you're exempt. So why would you be exempt if
it has קדושת קרבן? kedushat korban? So the answer is obvious. It
has, even though it has קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban, it has a
blemish and you can't bring it, and you can't bring it as
a קרבן. korban. You're only חייב chayav for שחט shechting as a
קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash for something that
could have been brought as a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So even though it has קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban, with
a blemish you're not חייב chayav for שחט shechting outside. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. השוחט בחוץ פטור. Hashocheit
bachutz patur. רב הונא מתני חייב. Rav Huna matni chayav. רב הונא's
Rav Huna version of this, again, whether it's our משנה, mishna, which
our משנה mishna actually does say חייב, chayav, or whether it's the
ברייתא braita that we just got through discussing, anyway, his version is
חייב. chayav. Now how could you be חייב? chayav? Even if you
didn't redeem it, it still has the blemish. ומוקים לה בדוקין שבעין
ואליבא דרבי עקיבא דאמר אם עלו לא ירדו. Umokim lah bedukin sheba'ayin
vealiba deRabbi Akiva de'amar im alu lo yerdu. He says it's talking
about a cataract of the eye, which is a blemish, but it's
extremely subtle. And because it's so subtle, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
although you're not allowed to bring it as a קרבן, korban, if
you brought it as a קרבן korban you don't remove it from
the altar. And therefore, since בדיעבד, bidi'avad, although you're not allowed to
bring this as a קרבן, korban, בדיעבד bidi'avad it could stay on
the altar, therefore if you שחט shecht it outside the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash you are חייב. chayav. Okay, so that is the one
curious case in our משנה mishna where it says if you שחט
shecht it outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you're חייב, chayav, and
the question is, okay, I understand it has קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban,
but it's got a מום, mum, so you can't bring it, how
could you be חייב? chayav? And therefore the גמרא Gemara says some
have the version פטור patur and some said חייב, chayav, but it's
a special case where it could stay on the altar. Now we
go back to the other line of the ברייתא braita from yesterday.
בין לפני פדיונן בין לאחר פדיונן עושה תמורה. Bein lifnei pidyonan bein
achar pidyonan oseh temurah.
And that was a very, you know, surprising line. This animal that
had קדושת קרבן, kedushat korban, then you, it got a מום, mum,
and then you removed the קדושה, kedusha, you were פודה. podeh. But
remember, it has residual קדושה. kedusha. How do we know it has
residual קדושה? kedusha? Because you can't shear it, you can't work it,
you're only allowed to שחט shecht it and eat it. It's exempt
from בכור, bechor, it's exempt from מתנות matanot after it's been redeemed.
Yesterday the ברייתא braita told us a new הלכה halacha that we
didn't know. It said that you can actually do a תמורה, temurah,
not allowed, but it will be effective. If I take another animal,
I got this animal that was redeemed and has this residual קדושה,
kedusha, and I take another animal and I say זה תחת זה,
zeh tachat zeh, which is what you do when you do a
תמורה, temurah, although again that's a sin, okay, so the הלכה halacha
is the second animal also becomes קדוש. kadosh. Now I would have
thought, we would have thought, I assume, that's only when the first
animal hasn't been redeemed. Even after it's been redeemed, even when it
has residual קדושה, kedusha, how would you think that you could go
ahead and do תמורה? temurah? And the משנה, mishna, ברייתא braita yesterday
said you can. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to look
at that scenario. Let's take a look. בין לפני פדיונן בין לאחר
פדיונן עושה תמורה. Bein lifnei pidyonan bein achar pidyonan oseh temurah. Whether
before or after you've redeemed it, even after you've redeemed it, even
though it's only residual קדושה, kedusha, it still will make the other
animal קדוש kadosh if you try to do an exchange. So אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah Bar
Avuha, in a way this is going to be almost a recap
of yesterday, a parallel of yesterday's discussion. תמורתו לאחר פדיונו מיתה. Temurato
le'achar pidyono meitah.
If you tried to do a תמורה temurah after the animal had
been redeemed, so this second animal you're going to have to let
die, you can't do anything with it. Once again, letting die. Why?
It's very similar structurally to the idea of giving birth after it's
been redeemed, which is what happens giving birth after it's been redeemed?
It has a derivative קדושה, kedusha, but the derivative קדושה kedusha puts
it in between two worlds. It's not קדוש kadosh enough to be
brought as a קרבן korban on the one hand, and it's not
קדוש kadosh enough to do a, to redeem it. So you're sort
of stuck. Now again, I still don't understand the same way I
didn't understand yesterday why you're fully stuck. Why not just שחט shecht
it and eat it like you could do with the mother? Okay,
but for some reason we understand that its קדושה kedusha is higher
than the mother, but it's still caught in between. So that was
yesterday was when the mother gave birth, okay, and here it's when
you did a תמורה. temurah. And he said, okay, so you can't
bring it as a קרבן korban because the original animal was only
residual קדושה, kedusha, you can't redeem it because it's only residual קדושה,
kedusha, and he doesn't say why you can't שחט shecht it and
eat it, but presumably it has some of its own קדושה kedusha
so you can't שחט shecht it and eat it, so you're totally
caught in between like you were yesterday, you have to let it
die. Now תוספות Tosafot says why it has a little bit more
קדושה kedusha than the mother, because תוספות Tosafot says part of what
a תמורה temurah does is we normally think, and this will be
a... ongoing discussion when we learn תמורה, Temurah, if I try to
say this animal was instead of that animal, that this and the
second animal becomes קדוש kadosh as well, we normally think that it's
a derivative קדושה, kedushah, that the קדושה kedushah of the first animal
transfers to the second. But תוספות Tosfos says there's another thing going
on as well. When I try to say this second animal becomes
קדוש kadosh instead of the first, I'm also giving it קדושה kedushah
because my verbally trying to designate it is a form of quasi-sanctifying
it. So therefore the קדושה kedushah of the תמורה Temurah is partially
a derivative of the original and it's partially the act, my own
act of designating is giving the קדושה. kedushah. And that's why תוספות
Tosfos says that this bizarre הלכה halacha to begin with, that even
though this animal is redeemed and it only has residual קדושה, kedushah,
the second animal could become a תמורה. Temurah. How could that be?
This is only residual קדושה. kedushah. Because my very act of designating
it is part of what gives it קדושה. kedushah. So since the
first animal was still in the world of קדושת קרבנות, kedushas korbanos,
although it was only residual, once it's enough in the world, the
fact that I tried to make it a תמורה Temurah gave קדושה
kedushah to it, but it's not just derivative קדושה. kedushah. So that's
what you're dealing with. And because it's not just derivative קדושה, kedushah,
you can't just שחט shecht it and eat it, but because it
also is derivative קדושה, kedushah, you can't bring it as a קרבן.
korban. So you're totally caught in between with this תמורה. Temurah. So
let's take a look. So תמורה אחר פדיונם מתה. Temurah achar pidyonam
meisa. You have to let it die. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's
the reasoning?
היכי ליעביד? Heichi liyavid? What should you do? לקריביה? Likreivei? Bring it
as a קרבן? korban? מכח קדושה דחויה קאתי. Mikoch kedusha dechuya kaati.
It's coming, it's derivative, or the way we just said it, it's
also a derivative קדושה kedushah and it's coming from the, the תמורה
Temurah was of an animal that only had residual קדושה. kedushah. So
this animal is defined by that as well and therefore of course
there's no way you're going to bring it as a קרבן. korban.
לפריקיה? Lifreikei? How about redeem it? לא אלימא למיפרק פדיונה. Lo alima
lemifrak pidyona. Same problem. The קדושה kedushah is so weak that you're
not able to redeem it. You need sort of a strong presence
of קדושה kedushah to transfer. Here the mother only had residual קדושה.
kedushah. You can't redeem residual קדושה, kedushah, so you certainly can't redeem
this thing which derived from residual קדושה. kedushah. Now why not שחט
shecht it and eat it, which like you could do by the
mother? So that I would say what sort of again drawing on
תוספות, Tosfos, because it also has to some degree its own קדושה
kedushah as well. So you're totally caught in between just like the
case of the kid which we discussed yesterday. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this, הלכך מתה. hilkach meisa. Therefore you gotta let it die. So
מתקיף לה רב עמרם. maskif lah Rav Amram. So רב עמרם Rav
Amram asked about this.
ותאכל במומה לבעלים. visachel bemumei lebaalin. Why not wait till it gets
a blemish and eat it? Now why would that, why should it?
I mean if you think about a normal קרבן korban after it
gets a blemish, you don't just eat it, you have to redeem
it. And he can't say wait for it to get a blemish
and redeem it, this because we already said it doesn't have a
strong enough קדושה kedushah that redemption works. So how, where does he
get a model of something that after it's a blemish you can
eat from it without any redemption? So do you know what animal?
I'll give you a hint. It has to do with the מסכת
masechet we're learning about. A בכור! bechor! Once it gets a blemish,
although it has קדושה, kedushah, you don't redeem it, you don't bring
it as a קרבן, korban, you eat it with the מום. mum.
You eat it, the כהן kohen eats it outside the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash with the מום. mum. So he says here we've got
a similar קרבן. korban. It doesn't have קדושה kedushah enough קדושה kedushah
to be brought. It doesn't have the ability to redeem it. Okay,
but why not look at the model of בכור bechor that once
it gets a blemish then even with its קדושה kedushah you're allowed
to eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Alright, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
לבעלים. lebaalin. וכי מה בין זו לתמורת בכור ומעשר? vechi ma bein
zo letmuras bechor umaaser? One minute, the גמרא Gemara says. Remember, this
is a תמורה Temurah and your implicit model is בכור. bechor. Let's
look at the story of what would actually be a תמורה Temurah
of a בכור bechor or תמורת מעשר Temuras maaser as well, which
has a similar הלכה. halacha. דתנן, detnan, תמורת בכור ומעשר, Temuras bechor
umaaser, if you have the תמורה Temurah of a בכור bechor or
מעשר בהמה, maaser beheima, הן ולדן וולד ולדן
עד סוף כל העולם, hein veladan uvelad veladan ad sof kol haolam,
whether they or their children or grandchildren or anything that sort of
derives from that קדושה, kedushah, הרי הן כבכור ומעשר, harei hen kebechor
umaaser, they're just like the original בכור bechor and
מעשר, maaser, ויאכלו במומם לבעלים, veyochlu bemumam lebaalin, and can be eaten
with the blemish. So he says look, I've got a perfect model.
Not only is it true about בכור, bechor, it's even true about
the תמורה Temurah of a בכור, bechor, that it gets the same
קדושה kedushah of the mother and the הלכה halacha is can be
eaten with the מום. mum. So this, although it's not a תמורה
Temurah of a בכור, bechor, it's a תמורה Temurah of I don't
know, a שלמים, shelamim, but since it's stuck in this in-between world,
let it be eaten with the מום mum like this model of
תמורה Temurah of בכור bechor and תמורת בכור. Temuras bechor. So the
answer is obvious. You can't just use a convenient model if it
doesn't fit. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said
back, זה שם אמו עליו וזה שם אמו עליו. ze sheim imo
alav veze sheim imo alav.
One case its status is defined by its mother, not exactly mother
because it's not about children here, it's about תמורה, Temurah, but by
the original animal, and this is defined by the original animal. What
does that mean? זה כולו תמורת בכור ומעשר. ze kulo Temuras bechor
umaaser. מעשר. maaser. So in the case of a תמורה tmura of
a בכור bechor and מעשר, maaser, fine, it's the קדושה kedusha is
similar to the קדושה kedusha of a בכור bechor and מעשר. maaser.
That was the origin and therefore what's the הלכה halacha of בכור
bechor and מעשר? maaser? כולו תמורת בכור מעשר מיקרי kulo tmuras bechor
maaser mikri
is what it's called. מה בכור מעשר במומן נאכלין לבעלים, ma bechor
maaser bemumon miachlim l'bealim, the same way the original בכור bechor and
מעשר maaser are eaten with a blemish to the... for the owners,
the owner for the בכור bechor being the כהן, kohen, אף תמורתן,
af tmuratan,
so even by the תמורה tmura it has the same הלכה, halacha,
נאכלין, miachlin, can be eaten with a מום, mum, with a מום,
mum, without being brought as a קרבן. korban. Fine, but we're not
dealing with בכור bechor and מעשר. maaser. We're dealing with a תמורה
tmura of a שלמים, shelamim, let's say, that was redeemed. וזה שם
אמו עליו. v'ze shem imo alav.
This is... has the name of its mother or its source. So,
תמורת קדשים
מיקרי, tmuras kodshim mikri, called the תמורה tmura of a קרבן, korban,
not of a בכור, bechor, of an עולה, olah, a שלמים. shelamim.
Fine. So מה קדשים לא מיאכלי, ma kodshim lo miachli, in the
same way a קרבן, korban, an עולה, olah, שלמים shelamim can't be
eaten with a מום, mum, אלא בפדיון, ela b'pidyon,
without redeeming it, אף תמורה נמי לא מיאכלי אלא בפדיון. af tmura
nami lo miachli ela b'pidyon. Here too, even with the blemish, you
do not say, oh, I have a good model I want to
use. No. It has to follow its own rules. What are the
rules about an עולה olah or a שלמים shelamim with a מום?
mum? You have to redeem it. So this is a תמורה tmura
of an עולה olah and שלמים shelamim with a מום, mum, you
have to redeem it. That's the only possible option. However, there's a
little problem. What's the little problem? You can't redeem it because it
has only weak קדושה kedusha because the mother... the original animal was
already redeemed, so the קדושה kedusha was only residual and it's weak.
אף תמורתן... הא לא אלימא למינתפס פדיונה. af tmurasan... ha lo alima
l'mitpas pidyona. And
this isn't strong enough to allow you to redeem it. So it
is very similar to the idea of the child. Okay, it's not
a strong enough קדושה kedusha to be brought as a קרבן korban
because it's... its derivative, it derives from a some derailed קדושה, kedusha,
it's not strong enough to be redeemed, that also needs a high
level of קדושה. kedusha. The only thing not being spelled out is
why not treat it just like the original animal? What's the הלכה
halacha for the original animal that's been redeemed? Shecht it and eat
it. Why you can't do that is not clear, but again תוספות
Tosafot says here, and we'd have to say something similar by the
child, children that we talked about yesterday, it also has some of
its own קדושה. kedusha. The act of תמורה tmura gives it some
of its own קדושה kedusha and therefore it is... shechting it and
eating it is also not an option. So the only thing you're
left to do is to let it die. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, תניא כוותיה דרב נחמן, tanya k'vasei
d'Rav Nachman, we taught like רב נחמן Rav Nachman who basically says
this point about letting it die. מניין לתמורת פסולי המוקדשין שמתה. minayin
l'tmuras pesulei mukdashim she'mesa. Here you go, an explicit ברייתא brayta that
says that point. How do you know the תמורה tmura of redeemed
sacrifices has to be let die? There's nothing you can do with
them. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ממעלה הגרה טמא הוא. mimalei hagera tamei
hu. So, this is basically... the פסוק pasuk says, וזה לכם הטמא,
v'ze lachem hatamei, these are the non-kosher animals, ממעלי הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה.
mimalei hagera mimafisey haparsa. From those that chew their cud and have
split hoof. Now of course then it goes on to list some
that have either only chew their cud or only have split hoof.
Right, but the introductory פסוק pasuk is, here are non-kosher animals from
things that split their cud... chew their cud and have split hoof.
Which חז"ל Chazal mean that it's telling you there's some things that
are normally kosher, have split hoof and chew their cud, and nevertheless
are not kosher. So now we have to find out what are
those things that are from a kosher species of animal and not
kosher. You understand how they're reading the פסוק? pasuk? The פסוק pasuk
literally reads, here are non-kosher animals among those with split hoof and
chew their cud. What it... and what it means is that have
only one or the other but not both. But חז"ל Chazal read
the פסוק, pasuk, here are the non-kosher animals among things with both
split hoof and chew their cud. Well, what's not kosher? Oh, there's
some animals that otherwise would be kosher but because of special circumstances
there's no way to eat it. Now what could that be? נבילה
neveila and טריפה treifa you don't need a פסוק, pasuk, that we
know. So let's take a look. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse
says, ממעלה הגרה טמא, mimalei hagera tamei, this is not kosher from
those that chew their cud. So therefore it's telling you what's not
kosher of an animal? This. Here's an animal that is a תמורה
tmura of פסולי המקדשים, pesulei mikdashim, right a very obscure case, but
there's no way to eat it. You can't bring it as a
קרבן, korban, you can't redeem it, you can't eat it. So here's
an animal that is like a non-kosher animal even though it's kosher.
This animal of a תמורה tmura of פסולי המקדשים, pesulei mikdashim, there's
no way to eat it and you have to let it die.
So the גמרא Gemara now says, one minute, הא מיבעיא ליה לחמישה
חטאות מתות. ha mibaya lei l'chamisha chatos mesos.
We need this פסוק pasuk that says that there are things that...
that cannot be eaten essentially, not to tell you this case but
to tell you another case of קרבנות korbanot that cannot be eaten.
What are other... other than עולה, olah, which obviously we know. What
are other קרבנות korbanot that there's no way to eat 'em? The
five חטאות chatos that have to be let die. Okay, this is
a משנה Mishna in תמורה. Tmura. It's too bad Michael isn't here,
he always likes the mnemonic of this. The mnemonic of this is
תמנע היתה פלגש לאליפז בן... לאליפז בן עמלק. Timna hayta pilegesh l'Eliphaz
ben... l'Eliphaz ben Amalek. תמנע Timna was the sort of concubine of
אליפז. Eliphaz. So you know, what the heck do we have to
know who was the concubine of אליפז בן עמלק? Eliphaz ben Amalek?
So sometimes the גמרא Gemara actually quotes that פסוק pasuk to point
out like, you know, every word in
the תורה Torah is
What are the five חטאות chatos *chata'os* that have to be let
die? So basically, the חטאת chatas, *chatas*, its whole identity is to
atone for sin. So when that is not a possibility, there's no
way it can be redirected and reused, and it has to be
let die. What are the five cases? So ו *vav* is ולד
חטאת chatas *vlad chatas*, if it has a child, the child has
the קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* of a חטאת chatas, *chatas*, but it's not
designated for that particular sin, so therefore you can't use it in
either way. It's caught between the categories. Okay, that's ו *vav*. ת
*taf* is תמורת חטאת chatas *tmuras chatas*. You transferred the קדושה kedusha
*kedusha*, so the second one has again קדושת חטאת chatas *kedushas chatas*,
but not for that particular sin. So there's nothing that can be
done with it. ו *vav*, מ *mem* is מתה בעליה *meisa ba'aleha*.
The owners died, so now the kids inherited this animal, but you
can't bring it for a dead person. The whole point is to
atone for a sin of a living person. That's מ *mem*. נ
*nun* is נתכפרו בעליו באחר *nitkapru ba'alav b'acher*. It got lost, and
they brought another קרבן korban, *korban* instead, and then they found the
original. Again, if it's not for that original
sin, it can't be brought as a קרבן korban, *korban*. And the
ע *ayin* is עברה שנתה *avra shnasah*. You delayed bringing it and
it's more than a year old. Okay, so those are the five
חטאות chatos *chata'os* that have to be let die. So says that's
what we learned from the פסוק passuk? *pasuk*, that there are kosher
animals that you can't eat, not for this תמורת פסולי מוקדשים *tmuras
psulei mukdashim*, but for חטאת *chatas* that have to be let die.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ההוא ממפריסה הפרסה טמא נפקא
*hahu mimafrisei haparshah tamei nafka*. Now remember the פסוק passuk. *pasuk* says
this you can't eat from things that chew their cud and have
split hoofs. So one of those phrases, chew their cud, is telling
us the תמורה tmura *tmura* of פסולי מוקדשים *psulei mukdashim*, and the
other phrase, split hoofs, is telling us the five חטאות *chata'os* that
die. But basically what we're learning from the פסוק passuk? *pasuk* are
certain animals from the קרבן Korban, *korban* world that there's nothing you
can do with them, you can't eat them, you can't bring them
as a קרבן *korban*, you have to lock them in a room
and let them die. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תניא
נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*, we taught similarly, ממפריסה הפרסה טמא *mimafrisei
haparshah tamei*, I'm sorry, תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*, מניין לחמשה
חטאות מתות *minayin l'chamisha chata'os meisos*, how do you know that there's
a category of five חטאות *chata'os* that there's nothing to do with
them and you have to lock them in a room and let
them die? תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, the verse teaches, ממפריסה הפרסה טמא
*mimafrisei haparshah tamei*, from those of split hoofs they are not kosher,
which means there are certain kosher animals that you can't eat and
that is the category of חטאות מתות *chata'os meisos*.
Now that we're done with that, we're going to digress a little
and talk about the idea of the five חטאות *chata'os* that are
מתות *meisos*,
and do we really learn it from a פסוק *pasuk*? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חמשה חטאות מתות הלכתא גמירי לה *chamisha chata'os
meisos hilchata gmiri lah*. We don't learn that from a פסוק *pasuk*,
that's a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*, that
there are five חטאות *chata'os* that we let die. That's normally the
assumption of the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara*. So how are you connecting it
here to a פסוק *pasuk*? אלא *ela*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
כי אתא קרא לתמורת אשם *ki ata kra l'tmuras asham*. Okay, you're
right, the extra פסוק *pasuk* is not saying the חטאות *chata'os* die,
it's telling you another case of an animal that can't be eaten.
What is that? The תמורה tmura *tmura* of an אשם *asham*. An
אשם *asham* is very much like a חטאת *chatas*, it's for sin,
okay, but it has slightly different הלכות *halachos*. When the five things
that happen to a חטאת *chatas* what happened to an אשם *asham*,
you can't actually get all five, but anyway you'll try to figure
out why not. Anyway, so what? Wait, what?
Very good. You can't get the child because an אשם *asham* is
a male. Oh, two points for James. Anyway, if most of the
five happen to the אשם *asham*, so whereas in a חטאת *chatas*
you would let it die, by an אשם *asham* you can't bring
it as a קרבן *korban*, but you have to wait for it
to get a מום *mum* and you can redeem it. So an
אשם *asham* actually has a similar הלכה halacha. *halacha*, but it can
be salvaged. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says maybe that's what the פסוק *pasuk* is coming to
tell me, not by חטאת *chatas* which I know הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*, but the parallel case by an
אשם *asham* like a תמורה tmura *tmura* would be one example, a
תמורה tmura. *tmura* of an אשם *asham*. Now the problem is that
then it's not the same point. The פסוק *pasuk* is saying cannot
be eaten, it's טרפה *treifah*. The תמורה *tmura* of an אשם *asham*
actually has a solution, it can be redeemed and eaten. But we'll
see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with it. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says okay, maybe כי אתא קרא לתמורת אשם *ki ata
kra l'tmuras asham*, for a תמורה *tmura* of an אשם *asham*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says first of all תמורת אשם נמי הלכתא
היא *tmuras asham nami hilchata hi*. We also don't need a פסוק
*pasuk* for that, it's a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, *halacha
l'Moshe miSinai*. What is the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *halacha
l'Moshe miSinai* of an אשם *asham*? כל שבחטאת מתה *kol sheb'chatas meisa*,
any scenario where were it to happen to a חטאת *chatas* the
חטאת *chatas* would be let die, באשם רועה *b'asham ro'eh*, by an
אשם *asham* you let it graze until it develops some מום *mum*
and you redeem it. So you can't tell me the פסוק *pasuk*
is for an אשם *asham*, same reason it can't be for a
חטאת *chatas*. That's all part of a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe
MiSinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. אלא *ela*, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says let's
go back to what we said before, לעולם חמשה חטאות מתות *le'olam
chamisha chata'os meisos*, really the פסוק *pasuk* is telling you the category
of חטאות *chata'os* that have to be let die. ואיצטריך קרא ואיצטריך
הלכתא *v'itztrich kra v'itztrich hilchata*. You need a פסוק *pasuk* and you
need a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*. דאי
מקרא *de'ei mikra*, had you just had a פסוק *pasuk*, הוה אמינא
hava amina לרעיה *hava amina l're'iah*. I wouldn't have known, you know,
you could say I wouldn't have even known to apply
it
to a חטאת *chatas* altogether. Who knows what animal that is? But
and even if I applied it to a חטאת *chatas*, I wouldn't
have known exactly what to do with it. Maybe I would say
you have to wait till it gets a blemish. קא משמע
לן הלכתא למיתה. So הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai tells us,
no, if it's a חטאת, I'm still saying this and then it
dies and so on. Okay, so that's nice. הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
LeMoshe MiSinai is very explicit. So then why do I need a
פסוק? So ואי מהלכתא v'ee m'hilchasa if I just had the הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai הוה אמינא havamina I would have thought,
היכא דעבר וקרי ואכל מהני חמישה חטאות heicha d'avar v'karei v'achal mehanei
chamisha chatos
if you transgressed and you ate from the חטאת that have to
be left to die, so how what's the nature of your transgression?
Maybe I would have said איסורא איכא issura ika you've done some
prohibited act, some generic prohibited act, but לאו ליכא lav leika you
don't actually transgress a biblical prohibition, right, 'cause you know הלכה Halakha
למשה מסיני can tell me the law or the rules, but it
doesn't actually prohibit something. The weight of a prohibition comes from a
פסוק. So okay, הלכה Halakha למשה מסיני tells me you can't bring
this as a קרבן, you can't eat it, but let's say I
did. What's the nature of the prohibition? Now the funny thing is
that the obvious answer should be the nature of the prohibition is
you're being נהנה מהקדש, neheneh m'hekdesh, right? So
and it's funny why we need to create yet another prohibition, but
but anyway that's what the גמרא gemara said.
And is there a case where we have הלכה halacha למשה מסיני
exists outside of the framework of the entire תורה? Torah?
Well
that's normally we have like הלכה למשה מסיני that tells
me like שיעורין. shiurin. Yeah, but
within the framework of... it's not... Right, normally it's within the parameters
and normally the answer to the question is so what are you
gonna do to me if I if I don't do it is
well no, those are the laws of that category, that's right. Exactly.
Well, not only that though, if it's telling me a detail of
סוכה, Sukkah, then I'll tell you you're not יוצא סוכה. yotzei Sukkah.
If it's telling me a detail of שמיטה, Shmita, I'll tell you
you're being עובר over on שמיטה. Shmita. So that really should have
been the answer here. If it's telling me a detail of a
חטאת, then I'll tell you that if you transgressed this, then you
were improperly benefiting from a חטאת and that's itself prohibited. So you're
right, I don't know why that was not a sufficient answer here.
Anyway, let's just read the upshot and the גמרא gemara says לאו
ליכא קא משמע לן דאיכא לאו lav leika k'mashma l'an d'ika lav
that there's also a לאו lav and that's why it says this
you cannot eat from the מעלה גרה ומפריס פרסה ma'aleh gerah u'mafris
parsah that if you put a חטאת in that category, you're telling
me that you also transgress a לאו. lav. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'is eima
the גמרא Gemara says and if you want I'll
say לאקושי דבר הבא ממעלה גרה לדבר הבא ממפריס פרסה l'akushei davar
haba mi'ma'aleh gerah l'davar haba mi'mafris parsah what's to connect the two
halves of the פסוק? One half is prohibiting the תמורה of a
פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin and the other is prohibiting a חטאת מתה,
chatas meisa, those special חטאות case, and it's linking the two. How's
it linking to the two? מה להלן במיתה אף כאן במיתה. mah
lahan b'meesa af kan b'meesa. Now that's pretty serious. It says the
same way one you let die, the other let die. Meaning, that's
telling me the idea which I started with, which is how do
I know that this animal that of the תמורה of פסולי מוקדשין
psulei mukdashin that you're totally, hey, how do I know you're stuck?
And B, if you are totally stuck, how do I know what
to do? So since it's linked to the חטאת מתה, chatas meisa,
since by the חטאת מתה chatas meisa there's הלכה למשה מסיני that
because you can't do anything you let it die, here too we
apply the same rule and since you can't do anything you let
it die. So the upshot of all of this is that the
one minute the תמורה of a פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin is like
the child of פסולי מוקדשין, psulei mukdashin, it's a derivative
residual קדושה, because it's residual it puts this in a never-never land,
but again a little bit curious why you can't just שחט shacht
it and eat it but because some degree maybe it also has
its own קדושה of a חטאת מתה, chatas meisa, so you're totally
caught both by the children and by the תמורה. What do you
do? You can't redeem, you can't bring as a קרבן, basically the
גמרא's Gemara, only solution is you let die and that also led
it to talk about the five חטאות that you have to let
die that you can't do anything with it which is the parallel
case and at the end very nicely compared the two and said
we actually learn one from the other that in these cases of
קרבנות korbanos where there's no solution you just have to lock them
in a room and let die, which again is, you know, pretty
shocking which we discussed yesterday.
Yeah, isn't it isn't it
an absolute הלכה למשה מסיני is the ideal state and the reality
of what the רבנן Rabbanan or חז"ל Chazal was dealing with people
who wouldn't want to lose the animal and you just can't let
them die, you try to find within the tradition some sort of
variant that people could live with?
I'm not getting exactly the...
In other words, in tradition everything you let the animal die but
people have to have money, מעות, ma'os, they
can't just let flocks and flocks die so there might be a
certain reality...
Well right, but we never have any evidence, I mean that would
actually be viol... I mean the גמרא Gemara never suggests that you
could do something other than this. This is the הלכה. How much
anyway these were all theoretical discussions 'cause at the time of the
גמרא Gemara nobody is living in this world anyway. But not theoretical
in the sense that the rabbis are saying one thing and people
do others. That happens all the time but the
גמרא Gemara, is
not.
If the גמרא Gemara is saying you're allowed to just hypothetically let
a stuff that's tortured and you know don't feed it and let
it die,
whether it's practical or not, it's giving you that principle that you
don't have to care about animals that you can then say to
yourself oh do I have to be kind to an animal? No,
I remember גמרא Gemara says you know under certain circumstances just let
it die. So it's giving it's opening to you the potential to
ignore a concept of צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim whether they
did it or not it doesn't...
Right, so I
think that is totally right. I got you when you talk about
three-year-old girls who are not the two-year-old. Right, whether it happened then
but it's saying you know this is okay, you can.
Right. Right, I think you're totally right. I'm very glad you're back
today because you weren't going to let us get away with this
but you're right, you need to say that. And that's absolutely correct.
Look, the reality is and that not it's interesting that in the
discussions of צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim these גמרות Gemarot are
not brought in, maybe because they feel that this just works on
its own plane, but nevertheless the הלכה developed based on a couple
of ראשונים Rishonim and then developed strongly in the period of שולחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch and post-שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch that you're allowed to
have צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim and allowed to have the
animal suffer if it is serving human needs.
And now on the one hand, you know, we could you know
feel I think very sort of morally shocked and offended by that,
but on the other hand, you know, if you were to say
the opposite then could you you know then would you ever do
animal experimentation for medical advancements and so on if you if you
don't allow the suffering for human needs? And let me just look
we should also be clear that we, myself very much included, are
all a little hypocritical about this because every time we eat meat
there is tremendous suffering, not just veal, people like to say oh
veal I'm going to be a צדיק tzaddik I'm not going to
eat veal. There's tremendous suffering that goes on in the raising of
animals in the meat industry to produce meat at the quantity and
price that we that we have and afford for. So if we
really would you know want to be principled about it then we
wouldn't be eating you know we would only be eating free-range meat
and we should not want to be doing you know animal experimentation
for advanced medical science and so on. So you know on the
one hand I agree that it's...
But that's human need though.
Well then the question if I can do it to fill my
stomach... But that's better. But if I can do it to put...
Okay so medical so medical advances is a
different perspective I think.
Right exactly. Medical advances is one thing. Okay medical advances is one
thing but right but to put meat in my stomach because I
like the taste of hamburgers is much less a valid sort of
you know concern than preventing the transgression here of you know of
קדשים Kodashim and so on. So you know so if any if
you buy into הלכה and to and to these things as מצוות
mitzvot and עבירות, aveirot, this is a much more serious concern than
eating a beef hamburger. So I agree that it's it's troubling but
it raises the larger question of what is the balance between human
desire and need and animal suffering and how to strike that balance
appropriately.
Also your attempt to distinguish between ritual and and benefit, I think
at some point in history, I don't know how far back you
go, you know probably maybe not the time of the גמרא Gemara
but in the time of the first temple I would say probably
yeah, the rituals were perceived as very real.
But they don't benefit... If we believe God said here are the
animals you can use them to benefit yourself, that's one thing, and
eating is benefiting and survival and all, but this does not benefit
the world by taking an animal and letting it...
That's a modern perspective.
But again you know as the other point goes well I we're
going to have to move on but the one thing I will
say is...
Letting an animal die for no reason.
But say that about all of קדשים, Kodashim, say that about all
קרבנות, Korbanot, you know that you're letting animals die for no reason.
Well people eat them.
Most of them, the כהנים...
Kohanim... עולות Olot which was a very standard קרבן, right? So within
that context whether psychologically you know for for the people or just
a larger statement about value as religious value and not just as
you know physical value. Alright but those are definitely the those are
the issues and it's important to be raised. Let's move on to
the next משנה. Mishnah. המקבל צאן ברזל מן העובד כוכבים. Hamikabel tzon
barzel min ha'oved kochavim. ברוך השם Baruch Hashem we are out of
all of that קדשים Kodashim stuff which we thought we had left
behind back in זבחים Zevachim but don't worry we're going to get
more of it later but we're out of it for now. So
anyway now we're back to dealing with contracts with non-Jews. So if
you accept a contract from a non-Jew to raise the kids of
its flock. Now remember קבל kabel does not mean just accept, it's
קבלנות, kablanut, you're basically contracting, okay? And קבלנות kablanut is you raise
somebody else's animals and you raise their sheep like the sort of
יעקב Yaakov and לבן Lavan story we're about to read and you
get a portion of the sheep. Okay so that's קבלה. kabala. מקבל.
mikabel. You are the קבלן. kablan. Now what is צאן ברזל? tzon
barzel? צאן ברזל tzon barzel is iron flock which is a phrase
used also in כתובות. ketubot. It basically means that you have the
person who gives you the sheep has protected investment. I'm giving you
my flock, we're going to estimate its value as a thousand dollars,
okay, I'm going to give it here to James, James is going
to raise it, we're going to split the sheep, but let's say
the flock dies or gets sick or something happens to them. James
is insuring me with an I or with an E I guess
anyway anyway
he's insuring the sheep and insuring me that he's going to give
me back the sheep worth a thousand dollars and if they're worth
less he's going to make up the difference. The original flock, okay,
that's צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. So for example it also gets used
when a woman gets married, she takes with her נכסי צאן ברזל
nichsei tzon barzel which means the property she takes into marriage, some
of it divided into two categories, but the צאן ברזל tzon barzel
part, the husband has usage of it, but when he dies or
if they get divorced, she gets back the property she brought in
and you know and it's protected of its original value. The principle
is guaranteed. Thank you very much. That's צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. Okay,
so the non-Jew gave this to the Jew, the principle is guaranteed
and the Jew is raising the sheep and getting half of the
kids.
Okay. ולדותיהן פטורין מן הבכורה. vladoteihen pturin min habechora. The children of
this flock are exempt from בכור. bechor. Why? Because first of all,
before we even get to the kids, the non-Jew owns the original
flock. So therefore he owns the mother, so the kids are exempt
from
בכור. bechor. ולדי ולדותיהן חייבין. vladai vladoteihen chayavin. The children of the
children...
now, excuse me, I misquoted. When it says ולדותיהן פטורין, vladoteihen pturin,
it doesn't mean the children of the original, they themselves don't have
בכור. bechor. It means the original flock had kids, those kids are
as mothers, as future mothers are exempt. So those kids from the
original צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, when they give birth, they're exempt. Now
why is that? The non-Jew only owns the original. So I might
have said because if we're going to split the kids, then he
has a portion in the kids as well, right? So therefore even
after we split them, maybe he was a part owner until we
split them in the kids and therefore I'm exempt. But interestingly that's
not the approach the גמרא's Gemara going to take. The גמרא's Gemara
going to take the approach the following: since the original צאן ברזל
tzon barzel are protected, principle and insured, if something happens to them,
where's he going to collect the difference from? The kids. So since
he has a right to take any of my of the kids
that even go into my you know that I earned, that are
mine, but he can take them to make up the difference, he
has a theoretical you know
like a presence, share, right, in the kids and therefore those kids
themselves as future mothers are exempt because in theory he could always
seize them to make up the difference. Okay, so that's the ולדותיהן
פטורין. vladoteihen pturin. What?
Like a lien.
A lien, right, exactly.
ולדי ולדותיהן, vladai vladoteihen, although maybe more than just a normal lien,
but yeah, like an intensified version. ולדי ולדותיהן חייבין. vladai vladoteihen chayavin.
Their grandchildren are obligated, meaning you have the צאן ברזל, tzon barzel,
he could have seized the kids, so they as future mothers are
exempt, but he could not have seized the grandkids. So the grandkids
as future mothers, when those grandkids give birth, that will be בכור.
bechor. The grandkids as future mothers are obligated.
So is this a general rule of נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon
barzel but that the first place you collect from is the kids?
No, not no.
This seems to be more about how the non-Jew would operate rather
than sort of maybe in principle in הלכה what you'd be entitled
to. Okay, so we'll see that as the גמרא Gemara will discuss
that, but it has much more to do with sort of sort
of I think the reality of that specific you know contractual relationship
and the implicit understandings. Okay, so let's look more. העמיד ולדותיהן תחת
אמותיהן. he'emid vladoteihen tachat imoteihen. Let's say the kids were put instead
of their mother. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says, so
תוספות Tosafot says based on the תוספתא Tosefta what it means is
the mothers actually did die and then I say to the non-Jew,
I say okay, so these ten sheep now, they are taking the
place of the mother, that's what you'll eventually be yours and you
know and so on. But nevertheless, if those sheep themselves die or
something happens to them, he can still make up that difference. So
basically what it just does is it just ups everything one generation.
You get it? Because I made the mothers die and I already
made these the substitute, so it just all gets up one generation.
רש"י Rashi says even without the mothers dying, if I just specifically
said to the non-Jew, although he always could have seized the kids
anyway, but I specifically said I want you will have a right
to have to make up the difference from the kids, that already
gives him as though an immediate right in the kids itself, not
just as a second stage. And therefore everything gets upped one generation.
Okay, so all the exemptions you know now apply one generation further
because everything moves up the food chain as it were. Okay, so
העמיד ולדותיהן תחת אמותיהן, he'emid vladoteihen tachat imoteihen, if the kid kids
of the original צאן ברזל Tzon Barzel were designated to get substitutes
or backups for their mothers, then ולדי ולדות פטורים, Vladei vladot p'turim,
the grandkids of the original צאן ברזל, Tzon Barzel, which are now
the kids of the substitutes, right, the grandkids of the original צאן
ברזל Tzon Barzel are exempt as future mothers, ולדי ולדי ולדות חייבים,
Vladei vladei vladot chayavim, the great-grandchildren of the original, which are only
the grandchildren of the substitutes, they as future mothers are obligated. Okay,
so basically the point is when I designate the kids as substitutes,
it all just extends one generation further. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says, אפילו עד עשרה פטורים, afilu ad asarah p'turim, don't let
end this at two generations, one generation, three generations, no matter how
many generations, they're all exempt. Why? שאחריותם לעובדי כוכבים, she'achrayutam l'ovdei kochavim,
they all have, you know, their lien or their obligation is to
the non-Jew, the non-Jew has a right to seize all future generations,
so therefore no matter how many generations, they're all exempt. Now, רחל
שילדה מן עז, Rachel she'yaldah min ez, on a totally unrelated point,
we're quoting a משנה Mishnah which really should be a separate משנה,
Mishnah, we had quoted this, you know, before as well, רחל שילדה
מן עז ועז ילדה מן רחל, Rachel she'yaldah min ez v'ez yaldah
min rachel, remember those cases, a sheep births something that looks like
a goat or vice versa, although they're both animals that are חייב
בבכורה, chayav b'bechorah, but the mother doesn't, the child doesn't look like
the mother, פטורה מן הבכורה, p'turah min habechorah, you're exempt, ואם יש
בו מקצת סימנים, v'im yesh bo miktzat simanim, if some characteristics look
like the mother, חייב. chayav. That's the whole case of נדמה Nidmeh
which we always are going back to. But anyway, we'll worry about
that later. Now we're going to focus on this whole thing about
if you were sharecropping the sheep raising, essentially it's a type of
a sharecropping. So let's take a look what the גמרא says. למימרא,
L'memra, says the גמרא, this implies, דכיון דלא נקט מרי זוזי, d'kivan
d'lo nakat marei zuzei,
since the master does not have the money, I took the sheep
worth a thousand dollars. I could have, I had an option, I
could have given him a thousand dollars, but I didn't, or I
could have, you know, maybe I don't know, put a thousand dollars
in escrow, but I didn't, and because that thousand dollars is not
in escrow or accessible by the original owner, so therefore ברשותא דמרא
קיימא, birshuta d'mara kaima, the sheep remain in the control of, in
the ownership of the original owner, which makes a lot of sense.
אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, it's exactly what we said. I'm
giving my sheep to James, he's insuring their value, but they're still
my sheep. Okay, and therefore that's why there's this exemption from בכור
bechor because they're my sheep and because the other sheep are theoretically
my sheep, etc., etc. Okay, so the גמרא says, רמיני, ramini, I'll
ask you on that.
אין מקבלין צאן ברזל מישראל, Ein mikablin tzon barzel mi'yisrael, you cannot
do this, again, מקבל mikabel does not mean receive, you cannot be
a קבלן, kablan, you cannot sharecrop צאן ברזל tzon barzel from another
Jew. So this whole arrangement James and I made is actually forbidden.
Why is it forbidden? מפני שהוא ריבית, Mipnei shehu ribbit, because it's
ריבית. ribbit. Why is it ריבית? ribbit? I'm giving James the sheep,
he's insuring their value. So if they were just totally mine, then
any loss would be my loss. But if he's insuring the value,
essentially what I've given him is like I've given him a loan.
Here's a thousand dollars worth of sheep. Okay, you're going to have
to pay me back a thousand dollars. That's what insuring the value
means, is that means that I don't suffer the loss, he suffers
the loss, because now it's only, ah, but what happens with the
kids? Who gets the kids?
You get some of the kids. Why? Why? So you're getting some
of the kids because as a, excuse me, forget that, of course
you get, I'm getting the other half, I'm sorry, I'm getting, you're
getting half, but I'm getting the other half. Why am I entitled
to half the kids? I loaned you my sheep, right? You should
be entitled to all the kids. Why are you giving me the
other half? Because I lent you my sheep. Okay, and because you're
paying it back not immediately but later, and therefore I am getting
a benefit for lending him my sheep, but it's not as a
loan of property, essentially as a loan of money. So it becomes
a type of a הלוואה, halva'ah, you're insuring the thousand dollars and
you're giving me back more than the thousand dollars, you're giving me
back half of the children. So that's אסור. assur. But why is
צאן ברזל tzon barzel allowed?
Yes, because if I suffered the loss, then it would be a
loan of property, it wouldn't be a loan of sheep, a loan
of money. I can rent you my car, right,
and you pay me rent, right? Any natural depreciation, not if you
get in an accident, but any natural depreciation is my loss. So
it's my car, it's not like a loan of money, it's a
loan of an object where I suffer the loss, and therefore you're
allowed to pay me rent. But if I give you the object
and you insure its value, you are taking full possession of it,
and then it becomes like a money loan, and once it's a
money loan, any benefit you're giving me back is ריבית. ribbit. Okay,
yes.
So a non-Jew can take interest
from a Jew, can take interest from a non-Jew, but we're saying
a non-Jew, a Jew and a Jew.
Oh, a non-Jew can take interest from a Jew,
but then why is it ריבית? ribbit?
Because both sides are Jews.
Oh, these are both Jews.
Yes, both Jews.
Oh, I see, we're talking about the non-Jew not being responsible for,
that's our משנה, Mishnah, but now the גמרא is comparing it to
a case of another משנה Mishnah about ריבית ribbit about two Jews.
Okay, this is in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, this is about, this
is in a פרק perek that's about ריבית. ribbit. Okay. So אין
מקבלין צאן ברזל מישראל, Ein mekabelin tzon barzel miYisrael, you can't do
it for two Jews, מפני שהוא ריבית, mipnei shehu ribbis, because then
as soon since you're since you are protecting the value it becomes
a type of a like a money loan and not like a
object rental and therefore it's a form of ribbis. אלמא, Alma, so
you see, ברשותא דמקבל קיימא, birshusa demakabel kaima, the fact that we're
calling it ribbis means that it becomes James's sheep, right? And therefore
or else it wouldn't be a loan. A loan means that the
money is fully given over to the other person who totally takes
possession of it. So since we're calling it ribbis, it means it's
totally in the possession of the receiver. So if that's true, says
the גמרא, why is there a בכור bechor problem? I'm the ישראל,
Yisrael, I got it from the non-Jew, I am now the full
owner of these sheep. I just owe him money. Okay? So if
all I owe him is money and he's not at all an
owner of the sheep, I should be חייב בבכור. chayav be'bechor. So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so said Abaye, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's
not difficult. הא דקביל עליה אונסא וזולא הא דלא קביל עליה אונסא
וזולא. Ha dekabel alei onsa u'zula ha delo kabel alei onsa u'zula.
The difference is is whether you accept the depreciation and that's זולא
zula and אונסא onsa is like the accident that happened or not.
So basically what he says is he makes our משנה Mishna a
special case. Classic צאן ברזל tzon barzel is exactly not this. Classic
צאן ברזל tzon barzel is is that you're protecting the owner from
any possible loss. But he says you're right, our משנה Mishna where
it's not totally in the possession of the Jew must be that
he that the non- that he's not protecting the non-Jew from loss.
And since he's not protecting the non-Jew from loss, they remain considered
to be the objects of the non-Jew. You got it? If I
take your object and I protect it from all loss, basically what
I'm saying is I now own your object and I owe you
its value, a thousand dollars. Because if it was still your object,
you would suffer the natural loss that occurred to it. So he
says our משנה Mishna where it's not where it remains the non-Jew's
object is that the Jew isn't protecting him from loss and therefore
it remains the non-Jew's object. So that's what the גמרא's going to
say. How can you call that צאן ברזל? tzon barzel? The whole
point of צאן ברזל tzon barzel is that you are protecting against
loss. So the גמרא says, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so
said Rava back to him, דקביל עליה אונסא וזולא צאן ברזל קרי
ליה? dekabel alei onsa u'zula tzon barzel kari lei? So it could
have been Rava. Okay. If you so if
you're if you are
not protecting him from loss, so דקביל עליה אונסא וזולא dekabel alei
onsa u'zula means that he, the non-Jew,
is accepting his own loss upon himself. So if the non-Jew is
accepting that the loss will be his loss, then how can you
call this צאן ברזל? tzon barzel? צאן ברזל Tzon barzel is that
it's not the loss of the original owner.
Okay. ועוד, Ve'od, my פירכא pircha number two, how could you sort
of, you know, what allows you to sort of, you know, limit
or divide the case from the משנה? Mishna? משנה Mishna says צאן
ברזל tzon barzel means all cases of צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. Even
if I would theoretically say there's a type of צאן ברזל tzon
barzel where you're not protecting against loss, and who knows why we're
calling it צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, but how do you get off
reading that into the משנה? Mishna? משנה Mishna says צאן ברזל tzon
barzel means all cases of צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. So that's not
the answer. So what's רבא Rava going to say? ועוד, Ve'od, oh
wait, a third
one. אדתני סיפא במקבלין צאן ברזל מן העובדי כוכבים, Adtani seifa bemekabelin
tzon barzel min ha'ovdei kochavim, since the end of the משנה Mishna
says that you can accept צאן ברזל tzon barzel from a non-Jew
in terms of ריבית ribbis because there's no problem about paying ריבית
ribbis to a non-Jew, לפלוג וליתני בדידיה, liflog u'lisni bedidei, why not
make a distinction even between two Jews? במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim
amurim, when can you not accept צאן ברזל tzon barzel from your
fellow Jew? דלא קביל עליה אונסא וזולא, delo kabel alei onsa u'zula,
when the original owner does not accept it, does not, does not,
you know, accept the depreciation. אבל קביל עליה אונסא וזולא, Aval kabel
alei onsa u'zula, if the original owner sort of accepts the depreciation,
then שפיר דמי, shapir dami, then it's okay because then it's not
like a monetary loan, then it's like renting an object. So it
didn't say that. You know, why didn't it say that? Because there's
no such thing as צאן ברזל. tzon barzel. There are other types
of arrangements where it's not like a loan, like it's like renting
an object. But there's no such thing of צאן ברזל tzon barzel
where the original owner retains the loss. The whole point of צאן
ברזל tzon barzel is he's protected against the loss. So you cannot
say that that's what's going on. There's no such category like that.
Okay. So we're back for a question. אלא
אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather Rava says, אידי ואידי דלא
קביל עליה אונסא וזולא, idi ve'idi delo kabel alei onsa u'zula, like
a classic צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, the owner, the original owner does
not accept depreciation, you you are protecting him against depreciation. And therefore
it's like you've taken total possession of it. So therefore we're back
to our question. Now we understand why it's ריבית, ribbis, it's not
renting an object, you've taken total possession of it. But now we
want to know why is there an exemption from בכור bechor if
it's your sheep now? והכא, Ve'hacha, by the way, this really is
fits into this week's פרשה, parsha, right? I mean יעקב Yaakov says,
right? זה לי עשרים שנה בביתך, Zeh li esrim shana beveisecha, I
took all the loss, אחטנה מידי תבקשנה, achatenah miyadi tevakshenah, right? So
צאן ברזל, tzon barzel, there you go. Anyway, so the גמרא says,
so what's פשט pshat in our משנה? Mishna? והכא גבי בכור היינו
טעמא, Ve'hacha gabei bechor hainu ta'ama,
here's the reason. דאתי עובד כוכבים בזיזי ולא יהיב ליה, De'asi oved
kochavim bezizei velo yahiv lei,
so the non-Jew will say, okay, give me back my thousand dollars
worth of sheep. And you say, oh, I don't have it, they
died, they were lost, or whatever. So where's he going to collect
it from? תפיס ליה לבהמה, Tafis lei le'behema, he'll seize the other
the animal, the other animal. ואי לא משכח ליה לבהמה, Ve'i lo
meshkach lei le'behema, I'm sorry, first he'll ask him for the thousand
dollars. You don't have the thousand dollars. So attach. So what's he
gonna first do? I mean, he probably wouldn't even go through the
process of asking for the thousand dollars, but in theory you're saying
you owe him it as a debt, you owe him a thousand
dollars. You don't have it, he's going to seize the original sheep.
לא משכח ליה לבהמה, Lo mishkach leih le-beheima, and if he doesn't
have the original sheep, they've died or there's been depreciation, תפסי ליה
לולדותיה. Tafsei leih le-valdoteiha. So then he'll get the kids of the
original sheep. דהרי ידו באמצע. De-harei yado be-emtza. So the non-Jew has
his hand in the middle of things, right? There's some people like
that, their hand is always in the middle of things. So the
non-Jew has his hand here in the middle. וכל ידו באמצע פטור
מן הבכור. Ve-chol yado be-emtza patur min ha-bechor. So basically it's saying
the reason you're exempt is not because he's an outright owner of
the original sheep, right? First of all, anyway, what explains the kids?
He's certainly not an outright owner of the kids. So the point
is you're right. When I, when the non-Jew gives James his sheep
here, James owns the sheep, non-Jew does not. But the reason you're
exempt is not because he owns the sheep, the reason you're exempt
is because he has a right to seize the sheep. And if
the sheep won't satisfy the debt, he has a right to seize
the sheep's kids. So anything that he has a right to seize,
even if James is the owner and not the non-Jew, that means
that he's got monetary rights in the sheep and therefore you're exempt
from בכור. bechor. Okay. And by the way, as I said, that's
anyway clear by the case of the kids. There was never a
הוה אמינא that he owns the kids, he only owns the mother.
But because he has the right to them, he has a monetary
lien or it seems like even more than a lien, that then
is enough to exempt. Is that what we're saying? The same is
true about the mother. Is it any different than saying, I mean,
this is not how we imagine this contract. The contract is he
goes first for the animal, then for the money. Right. So the
גמרא is trying to do it to explain, no, but I think
the גמרא is just trying to do it because they want to
conceptualize
it as if he owes money because it has to make it
consistent with the idea that it's ריבית. ribbit. And ריבית ribbit is
the model of, you know, as like a monetary type of a
debt. But you are correct and I'll just end by saying that
תוספות Tosafot raises the question because there's a discussion in the גמרא
that if the government should tax my sheep and they have the
right, the non-Jewish government, does that exempt me from בכור? bechor? Because
there's a, you know, because they can always seize my sheep in
terms of my either, you know, in terms of my tax debt.
And there's one opinion that says no. So תוספות Tosafot says what's
the difference? And תוספות Tosafot says there's a big difference because there
it starts, they don't start off with rights to the sheep. Here
they start off with rights to the sheep, so the presence is
much more of a sense of like a real ownership, not just,
and that goes back to your point, Dov, not just a generic
lien that you might be able to collect from this object. Here
it really starts with a real quasi-ownership. So even if fundamentally we're
going to conceptualize it as a loan, it's a loan that you
still retain real monetary rights and therefore that's the basis for the
בכור. bechor. Okay. There's Dov. He's
not,
I see what.